<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "REST_API_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-REST_API_Guide-Cluster_Level_Versions">
  <title>Compatibility Level Versions</title>
  <para>
    Each host managed by Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager has a version of <literal>VDSM</literal> installed. A more recent version of the Manager can manage hosts with a version of VDSM from an older version of Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization installed. However, since a VM may be migrated from host to host within a cluster, the Manager will not use features from a given version of VDSM until all hosts within a cluster have that VDSM version (or more recent) installed.
  </para>
  <para>
    This concept is represented in the API by each host being said to be at a <literal>compatibility level</literal>, corresponding to the version of VDSM installed. A <literal>version</literal> element containing <literal>major</literal> and <literal>minor</literal> attributes describes a compatibility level.
  </para>
  <para>
    Once all hosts within a cluster have been upgraded to a certain level, that level's <literal>version</literal> will appear under a <literal>supported_versions</literal> element. This indicates that the cluster's <literal>version</literal> may now be updated to that level. Likewise, once all clusters within a data center have been updated to a given level, the data center may then be updated to that level.
  </para>
  <para>
    For example, if you have a Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager <literal>2.2</literal> instance and you update to <literal>2.3</literal>, the API will report:
  </para>
  <screen>
&lt;host ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
  ...
&lt;/host&gt;

&lt;cluster ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
  &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
  ...
&lt;/cluster&gt;

&lt;data_center ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
  &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
  ...
&lt;/data_center&gt;
  </screen>
  <para>
    Once all hosts within a cluster have been updated to VDSM from <literal>2.3</literal>, the API will report:
  </para>
  <screen>
&lt;host ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="3"/&gt;
  ...
&lt;/host&gt;

&lt;cluster ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
  &lt;supported_versions&gt;
    &lt;version major="2" minor="3"/&gt;
  &lt;/supported_versions&gt;
  ...
&lt;/cluster&gt;

&lt;data_center ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
  &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
  ...
&lt;/data_center&gt;
  </screen>
  <para>
    The cluster may then updated to <literal>2.3</literal> and the API will report:
  </para>
  <screen>
&lt;cluster ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="3"/&gt;
  &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
  ...
&lt;/cluster&gt;

&lt;data_center ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
  &lt;supported_versions&gt;
    &lt;version major="2" minor="3"/&gt;
  &lt;/supported_versions&gt;
  ...
&lt;/data_center&gt;
  </screen>
  <para>
    This indicates that the data center may be updated to <literal>2.3</literal>
  </para>
</chapter>
